<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Background on Rattling</title><link>/docs/background/</link><description>Recent content in Background on Rattling</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Copyright (c) 2020–2024 rattling.org</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 18:59:06 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/docs/background/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What's rattling?</title><link>/docs/background/whats-rattling/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 16:04:48 +0200</pubDate><guid>/docs/background/whats-rattling/</guid><description>&lt;p>[Possibly move all this to homepage later]
A theoretical framework aimed at explaining order in nature, and specifically self-organization and adaptation in non-living dynamical systems. It is inspired by the quest to understand the general drivers of the origins of life: why non-living matter might spontaneously turn into living matter. It&amp;rsquo;s a new and active area of research, with some of the &lt;a href="https://rattling.org/core-questions/">core questions&lt;/a> having been resolved, and others very much open – &lt;a href="https://rattling.org/contact/">join our effort&lt;/a>!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Explaining order</title><link>/docs/background/explaining-order/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 16:04:48 +0200</pubDate><guid>/docs/background/explaining-order/</guid><description>&lt;p>Systems across physical scales and scientific domains exhibit order. Proteins fold, cells become tissues, and army ants form nests of their living bodies.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> However, to study order in nature, we must be careful in defining it: On the one hand, it refers to &lt;em>&amp;quot;&lt;a href="/core-questions/#strength-of-rattling-fine-tuning">concentration&lt;/a>&amp;quot;&lt;/em> – the system spending most of its time in a very small fraction of all possible configurations or states.&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> However, many natural systems that are trapped in some configuration can still be &amp;ldquo;disordered.&amp;rdquo; So a second requirement must be introduced – that these few selected configurations are also recognizably &lt;em>&amp;quot;&lt;a href="/core-questions/#environmental-information-encoding">special&lt;/a>.&amp;quot;&lt;/em> This can come in the form of spatial order – such as with pattern formation like crystals or zebra stripes, or in the form of function – such as with living organisms. While equilibrium thermodynamics helps us understand a special case of order – self-assembly – the case of order, and especially functional order, in presence of energy sources remains largely open.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Landauer's blowtorch</title><link>/docs/background/landauers-blowtorch/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 18:53:05 -0600</pubDate><guid>/docs/background/landauers-blowtorch/</guid><description>&lt;p>There can be no analogue of the Boltzmann distribution that applies to all nonequilibrium systems. The purpose of this entry is to explain why. At this stage, we will split our discussion into sections intended for different readers. For those seeking a physical discussion, read on. For those seeking a mathematical analogue, skip to &lt;a href="#a-mathematicians-perspective">this section&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Typicality</title><link>/docs/background/typicality/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 18:53:05 -0600</pubDate><guid>/docs/background/typicality/</guid><description>&lt;p>We claim that the Rattling hypothesis holds (i.e., predicts steady-state probability) for &amp;ldquo;typical&amp;rdquo; dynamical systems. On the one hand, &amp;ldquo;typical&amp;rdquo; here expresses an uncontrolled approximation – for a given system, it may be hard to determine a-priori how well Rattling will hold. On the other hand, it points to the intuition that Rattling should hold most of the time in real-world scenarios.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Nonequilibrium Boltzmann distribution</title><link>/docs/background/nonequilibrium-boltzmann-distribution/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 18:59:06 -0600</pubDate><guid>/docs/background/nonequilibrium-boltzmann-distribution/</guid><description>&lt;p>Just as the equilibrium probability distribution can be expressed in terms of local energy $U(x)$ via the Boltzmann law:&lt;/p>
$$p_{eq}(x) = e^{-\beta\, U(x)}/Z.$$&lt;p>
So Rattling tell us that we can express non-equilibrium steady-states in terms of local Rattling value $\mathcal{R}(x)$ as:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Formalizing rattling</title><link>/docs/background/formalizing-rattling/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 18:59:06 -0600</pubDate><guid>/docs/background/formalizing-rattling/</guid><description>&lt;p>The upshot of &lt;a href="/landauers-blowtorch">Landauer&amp;rsquo;s blowtorch&lt;/a> is that there can be no analogue of the Boltzmann distribution that applies to all nonequilibrium systems. As a consequence, it is not possible to analogously explain order in nonequilibrium systems. This suggests weakening the relation that the Boltzmann distribution constitutes, or narrowing the class of systems that must satisfy it. Rattling theory does both. We explain this point from a more mathematical perspective.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to use Rattling</title><link>/docs/background/how-to-use-rattling/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 18:53:05 -0600</pubDate><guid>/docs/background/how-to-use-rattling/</guid><description>&lt;p>Q: So what exactly can Rattling theory tell me for my specific system, experiment or question? How do I use it?&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>